<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catechisme, or manner how to instruct and teach children and others in the Christian faith appointed to bee read in all the lands and dominions of the late right and mightie prince, Frederike, countie palatine of the Rhein, one of the electors of the Holy Empire, and duke in Bauier / newly translated out of Latin and Dutch into Englishe.</title>
            <title>Heidelberger Katechismus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150926</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28823</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1880:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catechisme, or manner how to instruct and teach children and others in the Christian faith appointed to bee read in all the lands and dominions of the late right and mightie prince, Frederike, countie palatine of the Rhein, one of the electors of the Holy Empire, and duke in Bauier / newly translated out of Latin and Dutch into Englishe.</title>
                  <title>Heidelberger Katechismus.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henrie Middleton, for Iohn Harison,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, with loss of imprint date.</note>
                  <note>This edition omits mention of W. Turner as translator, and the prayer of Erasmus; adds marginal references to scripture.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸, E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformed Church --  Catechisms.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Cathechiſme or manner how to inſtruct and teach children and others in the Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>¶ Appointed to bee read in all the lands and dominions of the late right and mightie Prince, Fredericke Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Palatine by the Rhine, one of the Electors of the holy Empire, and Duke in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly tranſlated out of Latin and Dutch into Engliſhe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON. Printed by Henrie Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:2"/>
            <head>A note to the Reader.</head>
            <p>The firſte number of the notes in the margent ſignifieth the Chapter: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde number betokeneth the verſe: as they are vſually marked in the Bibles.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:2"/>
            <head>A Cathechiſme for Children.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich is the only comfort, both in life and in death?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That both concerning my ſoule and my bodie,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 6 19. 1 Theſſ. 5.10</note> whether I liue or I die,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 14.8</note> I am not mine owne, but belong onely vnto my moſt faithful Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.23.</note> who with his precious bloud moſt fully making amendes for all my, ſinnes,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18. 1 Iohn. 1.7. &amp;. 2.2.</note> hath deliuered me from the power of the Diuell,<note n="e" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.8 Hebr. 2.14.</note> and kéepeth me ſo,<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 6.39.</note> that without the will of my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, there can not ſo much as an haire fall from my head.<note n="g" place="margin">Matth. 10.30. Luke. 21.18.</note> Yea, and further, that all thinges muſt ſerue for my ſaluation,<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8, 22.</note> wherefore hee hath made me ſure of euerlaſting life, by his holy ſpirite,<note n="i." place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22. &amp; 5.5. Eph. 2 14. Rom. 8.</note> and maketh me prompt and ready from hencefoorth to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will.<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:3"/>
            <p> Howe many thinges are néedfull for thée to knowe, that thou maiſt come by, and inioy this comforte, that thou maiſt both liue and die bleſſedly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thrée:<note n="l." place="margin">Luk. 24.47. 1. Cor. b. 11. Tit. 3.3.4.5. &amp;c.</note> firſt, howe great my ſinne and wretchednes is.<note n="m." place="margin">Iohn 9.41 Rom. 3.</note> The ſeconde, by what meanes I may bee deliuered from my ſinne.<note n="n." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3.</note> The thirde is, what thankes I owe vnto my Lorde God for my deliuerance.<note n="o." place="margin">Ephe. 5.10. 1. Pet 2.9.10 11.12. Rom. 6.11.12.13. Math. 5.16. 2. Tim. 2.15.</note>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt part of mans wretchedneſſe or miſerable ſtate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BY what meanes ſhalt thou come by the knowledge of thy wretchedneſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the lawe of God.<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 3.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What doth the lawe of God require of vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That doth Chriſt in a ſhort ſumme teache vs. Mathew xxij. &amp; Luke x. Thou ſhalt loue the Lorde thy God, with all
<pb facs="tcp:28823:3"/>thy heart, with all thy ſoule, with al thy thought, &amp; with al thy ſtrength.<note n="b." place="margin">Luk. 10.27</note> This is the firſt, and greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement. And the ſeconde is like vnto this. Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thine owne ſelfe. And the whole law and Prophets hang vppon theſe two commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Canſt thou kéepe all theſe thinges perfectly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.10. 23 1. Iohn. 1.8</note> for I am readie &amp; diſpoſed of nature, to hate God &amp; my neighbor.<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 8.7. Ephe. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did God then make man ſo vntoward, crooked, and ſo frowarde?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No,<note n="e." place="margin">Tit. 3 Gen. 1.31.</note> for he made him good, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the likeneſſe of his owne ſelfe,<note n="f." place="margin">Ge. 1.36.27</note> that is, endued with true righteouſnes and holineſſe, that he ſhoulde rightly know God his maker, and hartely loue him, and liue for euer with him, to that end that he might loue &amp; prayſe him.<note n="g." place="margin">2. Co. 3.18 Col. 3.10. Ephe. 4.24.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, from whence ſprange vp this
<pb facs="tcp:28823:4"/>crooked frowardnes of mans nature?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the fall and diſobedience of our firſt father and mother, Adam &amp; Eue,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 3.5. Rom. 5.12.18 19.</note> by whom our nature is made ſo crooked &amp; naughtie, that we be all conceiued and borne in ſinne.<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 51.7. Gen. 5.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are we then all ſo wounded, that we be vtterly vnſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do any good thing, and diſpoſed and readie to all vice and wickedneſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes ſurely<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn. 3.6 Gen. 6.5</note> except that we be borne againe by the holie Ghoſt.<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth not God then do wrong to man, whiles he requireth of him by the lawe to doe thoſe things which he is not able to doe, performe, and fulfill?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Noe,<note n="e" place="margin">Ephe. 4.24.</note> for God made Adam ſo, that he might fulfil thoſe thinges, but he at the entiſement of the diuel,<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10.30. &amp;c.</note> &amp; by his owne ſtubbornes, both ſpoyled himſelfe and his after commers of thoſe godlye giftes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:4"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doeth God let go vnpuniſhed ſuch ſtubburnes, and departing from him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, he is by horrible meanes angrie,<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 5.12. Heb. 9.27.</note> both with our ſinns that are grafted in vs by nature, &amp; alſo with them that we afterwards worke and doe, and the ſame he puniſheth by his moſte righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement, with preſent and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhments, as hee doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce. Curſed is euerie man that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in all thinges that are written in the booke of the Lawe, to doe them.<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 27.26 Gal. 3.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then is not God alſo mercifull?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is in déed mercifull,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> but ſo that he is alſo righteous,<note n="c" place="margin">Exo. 20.5. Pſal. 5.5. 2 Cor. 6.14.</note> wherfore his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes requireth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that which is don againſt the moſt high maieſtie of God, ſhold be puniſhed with the greateſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes both of ſoule and bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſeconde part of the deliuerance of man.</head>
               <p>A. iiij.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:5"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THen, when as by the right iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, we are in daunger both of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting paynes, and of ſuch that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth here but for a time: is there yet any way or meanes whereby we may be deliuered from theſe paynes, and bee brought into fauour againe with God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God will that we ſhal make amends or ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his righteouſnes,<note n="d." place="margin">Exod. 25. &amp; 23.7.</note> wherefore we muſt néeds either by our ſelues, or by ſome other, content him<note n="e." place="margin">Rom. 8.3.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can we by our ſelues make amends or ſatiſfaction vnto him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By no meanes at all, but rather fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day, to encreaſe our debt.<note n="f." place="margin">Iob. 9.2.3. &amp; 15.15. Matth. 6.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can any creature in heauen or in earth, which is onely a creature, make ſatiſfaction, recompence, or amendes for vs and our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>None at all: For to beginne withall, God will not puniſh that in any other
<pb facs="tcp:28823:5"/>creature which is due to be paid by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="a." place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> and moreouer it can not (becauſe it is nothing but a creature) abyde the wrath of god againſt ſinne, and deliuer other from the ſame.<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 130.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What manner of man is to be ſought out, to be our mediatour and deliuerer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He which is in déede, a verie right man, and perfectly righteous, and yet more mightie then al creatures, that is he which alſo is euen verie true god<note n="c." place="margin">1. Cor. 15.21. Ier. 23.6. Iſai. 53.11. 2. Cor. 5.25 Heb. 7.16. Ieſ. 7.14. Rom. 8.3. Ier. 33.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is it néedefull that hee ſhoulde be a verie man, &amp; perfectly righteous?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe the righteouſneſſe of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame nature which hath ſinned, ſhould pay and make amendes for ſinne.<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 5.1.15.</note> But he that is a ſinner, can not paye and make amendes for other ſinners.<note n="e." place="margin">1. Pet. 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why muſt he alſo be verie GOD withall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A.v.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:6"/>
               <p> That by his godly power he may abide the burthen of gods wrath in his fleſh,<note n="f." place="margin">Iſay. 5.8. Act. 2.14. 1 Pet. 3.18.</note> &amp; may get againe and reſtore vnto vs, the righteouſnes and life which we haue loſt.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Io. 1.2. &amp; 49.10. Act. 20.28. Ioh. 3 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who is that mediatour which is both verie God and verie man, and perfectly righteous withall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 1.23. 1 Tim. 3.16. Luk. 2.11.</note> which is made vnto vs the wiſedome of GOD, righteouſnes, hallower &amp; deliuerer.<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe knoweſt thou this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Goſpel which God did open in Paradiſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> and afterwarde hath far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet it abroade by the Patriarches and Prophets<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 22.18. &amp; 49.10.11. Rom. 1.2. Heb. 1.1. Act. 3.22.23 24. &amp; 10.11. Rom. 1.2. Heb. 1.1. Heb. 10.7.</note> &amp; did darkely declare it as it were in a ſhadow, by the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and other ceremonies of the law <hi>(e)</hi> and laſte of all fulfilled it by his onely begotten ſonne.<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 10.4. Gal. 4.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then is ſaluation giuen by Chriſt to all men that periſhed in Adam?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to all: but onely to them that by a true faith are graffed into him, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or be partakers of his benefits or good déeds.<note n="g." place="margin">Ioh. 1.12 &amp; 3.36. Ieſ. 53.11. Pſal. 2.12 Rom. 11.17.19. Heb. 4.2. &amp; 10.39.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not onely a knowledge, wherby I do ſurely aſſent to al things<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 11.1.3 Iac. 2.19, Gal. 2.20.</note> which God hath opened to vs in his word: but alſo a ſure truſt<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 4.16. &amp;c. Iac. 1.8. Rom. 5.1.</note> kindled in my heart by the holy Ghoſte<note n="k." place="margin">Matt. 16.17 Ioh. 3.5. Ga. 5 2. Phil. 1.1.9.</note> through the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,<note n="l." place="margin">Rom. 1.16. Rom. 10.17.</note> wherby I am at peace with god, ſurely reckning with my ſelf and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that for giueneſſe of ſinnes, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, and righteouſneſſe, was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not onely to others but alſo to me<note n="a." place="margin">Heb. 10.38. Heb. 2.4. Mat 9.2. Eph. 2.7.8.9. Rom. 5.1</note> &amp; that fréely by the mercie of God, for the deſeruing of Chriſt alone.<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 3.24 25. Gal. 2.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are thoſe thinges that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man muſt néeds beléeue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All thinges that are promiſed in the Goſpel,<note n="c." place="margin">Ioh. 20.31. Mat 28.20.</note> the ſum wherof is conteined
<pb facs="tcp:28823:7"/>in the créede, or articles of our faith, wherein is ſhortely conteined, as in a certaine ſhort ſumme, the chéefe points of the Catholike and vndoubted faith of all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the Créede ye ſpeake off?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Beleue in God the Father almighty, maker of heauen and earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely begotten ſonne our Lord. Which was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the virgin Mary. Suffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified deade and buried, went down into hell. The thirde day he roſe againe from the deade. And went vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſitteth there at the right hande of God the father Almighty. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence ſhall he come to iudge the quick and the dead. I beléeue in the holy Ghoſt. That there is a catholike church. A commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints. Forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. The riſing againe of the fleſh. And the life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into how many parts is this Créede
<pb facs="tcp:28823:7"/>deuided?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into thrée partes: the firſt is of the euerlaſting father, and of our creation. The ſeconde is of the ſonne, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption or deliuerance. The thirde is of the holy Ghoſt, and making of vs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and fauing vs from ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When as there is but one onely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God:<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 6.4. Ephe. 4.5.6.</note> Why nameſt thou thrée: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, the ſon, &amp; the holy ghoſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe God hath ſo opened him ſelfe in his worde,<note n="b" place="margin">Ieſ. 16.1. Luk. 4.18. pſa 110.1. Math. 3.16.17. &amp; 28.19. 1. Ioh. 5.7.</note> that theſe thrée ſundrie perſons are that one, true, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Father.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVHat doeſt thou beléeue, when thou ſaiſt, I beléeue in god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almightie, maker of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I doe beléeue that the euerlaſting fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lorde Jeſus Chriſt, whiche hath made of nothing heauen &amp; earth,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:8"/>and all things that are therein:<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 1.6. Pſal. 33.6.</note> and with his euerlaſting counſell and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, vpholdeth and gouerneth all the ſame<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 104. &amp; 115.3. Matth 10.29. Heb. 1 3. Rom. 11.36</note> for Chriſtes ſake, is my god &amp; my father:<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 1.12. Rom. 8.15. Gal. 4.5.6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>7. Ephe. 15.</note> and therefore ſo truſt and reſt in him, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I do not doubt but he will prouide for me all things néedeful both for my ſoule and<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 55.23. Matth 6.25. 26. Luk. 12.22.</note> body, and that he wil alſo turne vnto my ſaluation, all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilles and troubles that he layeth vpon me<note n="a" place="margin">Rom 8.28.</note> in this troubleſome life, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee can doe it, as an almightie God,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 10.12</note> and will do it, as a gentle Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 6.26 &amp; 7.9.10.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the prouiſion, or prouidence of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The almightie power of God<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 17.25. &amp;c.</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in euerie place, whereby it holdeth vp as it were with a hande<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 8.2.3.</note> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth heauen and earth and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in ſo much that thoſe thinges that growe vppon the earth, as raine, alſo faire weather, and drineſſe, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in bearing, and barreuneſſe, meate and drinke,<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 5.24. Act. 14.17.</note> health and ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:8"/>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 9.5.</note> riches and pouertie:<note n="h" place="margin">Prouerb. 22.2.</note> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, all things fall and come vnto vs, not without aduiſe or by chance, but by his fatherly aduiſed counſell, will, and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profite haue we by this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the creation, and prouidence of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in aduerſitie we may bee pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 5, 3. Iac. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. Iob. 1.21.</note> and in proſperitie thankeful,<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 8.10. 1, Theſſ. 5.18</note> and in time to come, we may haue a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry good hope in God our moſt faithfull Father,<note n="l" place="margin">Ro. 5.4.5.6.</note> knowing that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that can draw vs away from his loue,<note n="m" place="margin">Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 38.39.</note> for all creatures are ſo in his power that without his will they can not onely doe nothing, but euen not ſo much as to ſtir or moue.<note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 1.12. &amp; 2.6. Pro. 21. 1 Act. 17.25.28.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sonne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHy is the Son of God called Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that is, the ſauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe hee ſaueth vs from all our
<pb facs="tcp:28823:9"/>ſinnes,<note n="a." place="margin">Matth. 1.21 Heb. 7.25.</note> and as no ſaluation ought to be craued of any other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there none be found in other, but in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>dne.<note n="b." place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then whether doe they beleeue in the onely ſauiour Ieſus, which ſéeke happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſaluation of ſaintes, or of them ſelues, or of any other thing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No, for although they boaſte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and reidice in him as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in their wordes, yet for all that, in verie déede they denie the onely ſaviour Ieſus,<note n="c." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.13. &amp; 31. Ga. 5.4</note> for either muſt Ieſus not be a perfect ſauiour, or elſe al they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiue him with a true faith for a ſauiour, haue in their poſſeſſion in him, al thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie vnto ſaluation.<note n="d." place="margin">Heb. 12.2. Ieſ. 96. Col 1 19.20. &amp;. 2.10. Iohn. 1.16</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is he called <hi>Chriſtus;</hi> that is, anointed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe he was ordeyned of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; was annointed of the holy ghoſt;<note n="e." place="margin">Pſal. 45.8. Heb. 1.9.</note> the higheſt prophet and doctour,<note n="f." place="margin">Deutr. 18.15 Act. 3.22.</note> which opened vnto vs the ſecret coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 1.18. &amp; 15.15.</note> and all the will of his father con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:28823:9"/>our redemption &amp; deliuerance. And the high Prieſt, who with one ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice or offering of his bodie and no moe: hath bought vs againe, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually maketh interceſſion to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs.<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.34. &amp; 5.9.10.</note> And a King which gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs with his worde and his ſpirite, and defendeth and kéepeth the ſaluation which we haue gotten by him.<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 2.6. Luk. 1.33. Matth. 28.18. Ioh. 10.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But why art thou called a chriſtian?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe through faith I am a member of Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="c." place="margin">Act. 11.26. 1. Cor. 6.15.</note> and am partaker of his annointing,<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 2.27. Ieſ. 59<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21. Act. 2.17. Ioel. 2.28.</note> ſo that I confeſſe his name,<note n="e" place="margin">Mar 8.38.</note> and giue my ſelf vp vnto him, to be a liuing offering of thankfulneſſe,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 12.1. Apoc. 5.8.10. 1 Pet. 2.9 2. Tim 2.12 Rom 6.12 13. Apoc 1.6</note> in this life to fight againſt ſinne and Sathan with a frée and good conſcience, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afterward I may holde and enioy the euerlaſting kingdome with Chriſt ouer all creatures.<note n="g" place="margin">1 Ti. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For what cauſe is Chriſt called the onely begotten ſonne of God, when we are alſo the ſonnes of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:10"/>
               <p> Becauſe Chriſte is onely the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and naturall ſonne of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euerlaſting,<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.18. Heb. 1.2</note> and wee are but ſonnes chooſen and taken vp of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely of fauoure for Chriſtes ſake.<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8.15. Ephe. 1.6</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why calleſt thou him our Lorde?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe he buying againe our bodies and ſoules from ſinne, not with gould nor ſiluer, but with his pretious bloud, and deliuering them from all power of the diuel: hath claymed vs for his owne proper ſeruaunts, belonging to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lorde or Maiſter.<note n="k" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18 19. &amp; 2.9. 1. Cor. 6.20. &amp; 7.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What beléeueſt thou, when thou ſaieſt: he was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the virgin Mary?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſonne of God, which is,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.1. &amp; 17.5. Rom. 1.4.</note> &amp; abideth true and euerlaſting God,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very true nature of man, of the fleſh and bloud of the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.14. Gal. 4.4.</note> by the working of the holy ghoſt,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:10"/>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 1.18 20. Luk. 1.35</note> that he might be alſo with all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſéede of Dauid<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 132.12 Rom. 1.3.</note> like vnto his brethren in all thinges,<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 2.7</note> ſauing onely in ſinne.<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.7.26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profit takeſt thou of the holy conception and byrth of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he is our meane or mediator,<note n="h" place="margin">He. 2 16.17</note> and with his innocentnes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte holines couereth my ſinnes in the which I am conceiued, to come into the ſight of God.<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1 1. Cor. 1.30</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What beléeueſt thou, when thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt he ſuffered?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he, all the time of his life while hee was here vppon earth, but ſpecially at his laſt time, did ſuffer the wrathe of GOD againſte the ſinne of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde,<note n="k" place="margin">1. Pet 2 24 &amp;. 3.18. Ieſ. 53.12</note> that with his paſſion as one ſacrifice once for all,<note n="l" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2. &amp; 4.10. Rom. 3.25</note> he ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe mercie, &amp; ſhoulde deliuer both our bodies and our ſoules from euerlaſting dampnation, &amp; get vs the grace of god,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:11"/>and righteouſneſſe, and euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For what cauſe did hee ſuffer vnder iudge Pilate?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he being innocent, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 25.14. Ioh. 19.8.</note> before a ciuill iudge, might deliuer vs from the ſtraight iudgement of God which we had deſerued, &amp; ſhould haue ſuffered if Chriſt had not ſuffered this ſharpe iudgement for vs.<note n="b" place="margin">pſal. 65.2.5 Ieſ. 53.2. Cor 5.21. Gal. 3.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is there any other cauſe beſide, why that he ſhold rather ſuffer on the croſſe, then die any other death?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, there is one in déede: for by this thing I am aſſured that he tooke vpon himſefe the curſe which was due vnto me. For the death of the croſſe was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of God.<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 21.23 Gal. 3.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why muſte Chriſt humble himſelfe euen vnto the death?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe that the iuſtice and trueth of God<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> could not be contented and ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:28823:11"/>for our ſinnes by any other meanes but by the death of the ſonne of god.<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 2.9.14 15. Phil. 2.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why was he alſo buried?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That thereby we ſhould haue ſure wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that he was truely deade, and not feynedly.<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 13.29. Mat. 27.60. Luk. 23.35. Ioh. 19.38.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when as Chriſt died for vs, why muſt we alſo die?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our death is not a making of amends for our ſinnes: but a dying from Sinne, and a going into euerlaſting life.<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 5.24. Phil. 1.23. Rom. 7.24.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profite doe we further receiue by the ſacrifice and death of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That by the vertue of his death our olde man is crucified<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.6.7 8.11.12.</note> killed and buried with him, that the euil deſires and luſts of the fleſh ſhould not afterward raigne in vs,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> but that we ſhould offer our ſelues vnto him an offering of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:12"/>
               <p> Why is it further ſaide: he went down into hell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in my grieuous temptations &amp; aſſaltes, I might ſtay &amp; make ſure my ſelfe by this comforte, that my Lorde Ieſus Chriſt by vnſpeakable verations and griefs, painful troubles and feares of mind, into the which both before and moſt of all when he ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged on the croſſe, he was caſte into hath deliuered mee from the ſorrowful griefe and paines of Hell<note n="d" place="margin">Ieſ. 53.10. Mat. 27.46.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profite haue wee by the riſing againe of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt that by his riſing againe he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came death, that he might make vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his righteouſneſſe, which hee had purchaſed vnto vs by his death.<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.17 45.55. Rom. 4.25. 1. Pet. 1.3 21.</note> Moreouer, we are alſo ſtirred vp by his power, vnto a newe life.<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6 4. Col. 3.1.5 Eph. 2.21</note> And the thirde profite is, that the reſurrection of our heade Chriſt, is a pledge and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect aſſurance vnto vs that we ſhall riſe againe in glorie.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Co. 15.12 Rom. 8.11</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:12"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe vnderſtandeſt thou this, that he is gone vp into heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Chriſte (the Apoſtles looking on) was taken vp from the earth into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 1.9 Mat. 28. Mar. 16. Luk. 24.</note> and yet ſtil is ther for our ſakes,<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 4.24. &amp; 7.25.9.11 Rom. 8.34. Ephe. 4.10 Col 3.1.</note> &amp; will be vntill he ſhall come againe to iudge the quicke and the dead.<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 1</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall Chriſte not then bée with vs vntill the end of the worlde as hee hath promiſed?<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 28.20. Mat. 24.30.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt is true God and true man, and ſo according vnto his mans nature, hee is not nowe vppon the earth,<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 26 11. Ioh. 16.28. &amp; 17.11. Act. 3.21.</note> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Godly nature, maieſtie, grace, and ſpirite, he is neuer away from vs.<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 14.17. &amp;c. &amp; 16.28. &amp; 16.13. Ephe. 4.8 Auguſtinus Tract. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ann. 50.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whether by this meanes are the two natures of Chriſte pulled in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or no, if Chriſtes manhoode bee not whereſoeuer his godheade is?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, for when as the Godheade of
<pb facs="tcp:28823:13"/>Chriſte cannot bee incloſed nor holden within anie certeine compaſſe, and is preſent in euerie place,<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 7.49. &amp; 17.28. Ier. 23.24.</note> it muſt néeds be a good argument that his Godhead is without the nature of his manhoode which he hath taken vppon him, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth farther, and yet for all that it is faſt in the ſame, and abideth perſonally ioyned therevnto.<note n="h" place="margin">Col. 2.9. Ioh. 3.13. &amp; 11 15. Math. 28.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What fruite haue we by the going vp of Chriſt into heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt that he maketh interceſſion for vs in heauen, vnto the father.<note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.1.2 Rom. 8.34.</note> Then that we haue our fleſhe in heauen, that thereby we may be ſurely aſſured, as by a ſure pledge, that hereafter hee will take vs that are his members, vnto him which is our heade.<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 14.2. &amp; 20.17. Eph. 2.6.</note> Thirdly, that he ſendeth to vs his ſpirit in the ſtede of a pledge<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 14.16. &amp; 20.7. Act. 2.2. Cor. 1.22.2. Cor. 5.5.</note> betwéene him &amp; vs, by whoſe ſtrong working, we ſéeke not earthly things, but the things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are aboue, wher he is ſitting at the right hand of god.<note n="d" place="margin">Col. 3.1. Phi. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is it further ſaide, that he is ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of God?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:13"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe Chriſt therefore is gone vp into heauen, to ſhew that he is the head<note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.20.21.22.23. &amp; 5 23. Coll. 1.18.</note> of the Church by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth all thinges.<note n="f" place="margin">Matth. 28.18. Ioh. 5.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profite is this glorie of our head Chriſt vnto vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt that through his holy ſpirit, he powreth into vs, (his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers) heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gifts,<note n="g" place="margin">Ephe. 4 10.</note> the next is, that he ſhieldeth and defendeth vs by his might againſt all our enimies.<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 2.9. &amp; 110.12. Ioh. 10 28. Ephe. 4.8</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What comfort haſt thou by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe of Chriſt, to iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick and the dead?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in all my perſecutions &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles I do look vp to heauen, holding my head cherefully vp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelf ſame iudge<note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 21.28. Rom. 8.23.33 Phil. 3.20. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. 2.13.</note> which purpoſedly before did deliuer himſelf to the iudgment of God for me, and hath taken away al curſe from me, which ſhal caſt all his and my enimies into euerlaſting paine,<note n="a" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 6.7 1. Theſ. 4.16 Matth. 25.41 Matth. 25.34</note> &amp; ſhall bringe
<pb facs="tcp:28823:14"/>mee with all other choſen perſons, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heauenly ioyes and euerlaſting glorie.<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 25.34.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the holy ghoſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVHat doſt thou beléeue, of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that he is a true and euerlaſting God, with the euerlaſting father and the ſonne<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 1.2. Ieſ 48.16.1. Cor. 3.16.1. Cor. 6.19. Act. 5 3.4</note> Secondly that he is giuen vnto me,<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 28 19.2. Cor. 1 21.22.</note> that by true faith hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me partaker of Chriſt, and all his good déedes.<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 3.14. 1. Pet. 1.2. 1. Cor. 6.17</note> And thirdly, comforteth mee, and abideth with mee for euer.<note n="f" place="margin">Act 9.31. Ioh. 14 16. 1. Pet. 4.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is thy beliefe concerning the holy and Catholike Church of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beléeue that the ſonne of God doth<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 10.11.</note> gather from the beginning of the world vnto the end)<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 71.18 1. Cor. 11.26.</note> out of whole man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 26.4.</note> a choſen<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8.29.30. Eph. 1.10.11.12.13. 1. Pet 1.20.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany by the ſpirit &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word,<note n="l" place="margin">Ieſ. 59.21. Rom. 1.16. &amp; 10.14.17. Eph. 5.26.</note> agréeing together in a true<note n="m" place="margin">Act. 2.46. Eph. 4.3.4.5.</note> faith, &amp; that he defendeth and ſaueth
<pb facs="tcp:28823:14"/>the ſame,<note n="n" place="margin">Matth. 19 18. Ioh. 10.28. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.30.</note> and that I am one liuely members of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie,<note n="o" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.21. 3. Cor. 13.5</note> and ſhall ſo abide for euer.<note n="p" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.19.1 1. Cor. 1 8.9. Rom. 8.35.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What meaneſt thou by the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and felowſhip of ſaintes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that all and euerie one that beleeueth, are in common partakers of Chriſte and of his good déedes, as his members and parts of his body,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.3 Rom. 8.32. 1 Cor. 12 13 21 1. Cor. 6.17.</note> and then that euerie man ought willingly, readely, and carefully, to beſtowe the giftes which hee hath receyued, to the common profite and health of all men.<note n="b" place="margin">Cor. 13.5 Phil. 2.4.5.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What beléeueſt thou of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That GOD for the ſatiſfaction or full recompence that Chriſt hath made<note n="c" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2 Cor. 5.19.21.</note> hath put out the remembraunce of my ſinnes, and alſo of that my crooked nature and wickedneſſe wherewith I muſt fighte all my lyfe time,<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 31.34 Pſ 103.3.10.12 Rom. 7.24.25 Rom 8 1.2.3.</note> and that hee will freely giue vnto mee
<pb facs="tcp:28823:15"/>the righteouſnes of Chriſt, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſhall not come at any time to iudgement, to be condempned.<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What comfort haſt thou by the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That not onely my ſoule (after that it ſhall departe from the bodie) ſhall ſtreight way be taken vp vnto Chriſte her head,<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 23.43 Phil. 1.23.</note> but alſo that this my fleſhe (raiſed vp by this power of Chriſt) ſhal be ioyned againe vnto my ſoule, &amp; ſhall be made like vnto the glorious body of Chriſt.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53.54. Iob. 19 25.26. 1. Ioh. 3.2. Phil. 3 21</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What comfort takeſt thou of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of euerlaſting life?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That for as much as I féele alreadie, the beginning of euerlaſting life in my<note n="a" place="margin">2. Co. 5.2.3</note> hearte, it ſhall afterwarde come to paſſe, that after this life, I ſhal come to full and perfect bleſſedneſſe, wherein I may praiſe God for euer, which bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neither eye hath ſéene, nor eare hath hard, neither the thought of man is able
<pb facs="tcp:28823:15"/>to reach vnto.<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when thou beleueſt all theſe thinges, what profite haſt thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I am righteous in Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and an heire of euerlaſting life.<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 2.4. Rom. 1.17. Ioh. 3.36.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe art thou rightuous before God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely by faith or beléefe in Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 2.3.21.22.24. Gal 2.16. Eph. 2.8 9. Phil. 3.8.9.</note> in ſomuch that although my concience did accuſe me, that I haue ſinned grieuouſly againſt all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God, and haue kepte perfectly neuer a one of them,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 3.9. &amp;c.</note> &amp; am alſo readie and diſpoſed yet ſtill to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> yet for al that (ſo that I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all theſe good déeds of Chriſt by a true faith of my mind) the perfecte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction or amends making, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holyneſſe of Chriſte, is counted and giuen vnto me by the only mercy of God,<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 3.22. Ioh. 3.18. Tit. 3.5. Deut. 9.10. Ezech. 36.22. Rom. 3.24 Ephe. 2.8.1. Ioh. 2.2.1. Ioh. 2.1. Rom 4.4.2. Cor. 5.19.</note> euen as though I had
<pb facs="tcp:28823:16"/>neuer doe any ſinne, neither any ſpot ſhoulde cleaue vnto mee: and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, as though I had fulfilled in mine owne perſon, the obedience whiche Chriſt hath fulfilled and performed for me<note n="h." place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why doeſt thou holde that thou art made righteous by faith alone?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not becauſe I doe pleaſe God with the worthineſſe of my faith, but becauſe the amendes making or ſatiſfaction, righteouſneſſe and holineſſe of Chriſt, are my righteouſneſſe before god,<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30. &amp;c.</note> &amp; I cannot take holde thereof, and apply the ſame vnto me by any other means, then by faith alone.<note n="b." place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why are not our good workes accounted righteouſneſſe: or at the leaſt ſome parte of righteouſneſſe before God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>becauſe that righteouſnes that muſt ſtande faſte before the iudgement of God, muſt be in all pointes perfect and
<pb facs="tcp:28823:16"/>agréeing with the word of God,<note n="c." place="margin">Gal. 3.10. Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.26</note> and all our good workes (euen the moſt holy &amp; perfecteſt workes that we do in this life) are vnperfecte and defiled with ſinne.<note n="d." place="margin">Ieſ. 64.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe doe our good workes deſerue nothing, when as God doth promiſe that hee will giue a rewarde for them, both in this life, and in the life to come?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That rewarde is giuen not of deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but of fauour.<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 17.10</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth not this learning make men to be careleſſe, Godleſſe, and of a looſe life?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No, for it is not poſſible but that they that are grafted into Chriſte through faith, ſhall bring forth good and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fruites.<note n="f." place="margin">Matth. 7.18. Ioh. 15.5.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sacramantes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THen, ſéeing that onely faith maketh vs partakers of Chriſt &amp; of his good
<pb facs="tcp:28823:17"/>déedes, from whence commeth this faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the holy Ghoſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 2.8. &amp; 6.23. Ioh. 3.5. Phil. 1.29.</note> who kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it in our heartes through the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, and ſtrengtheneth the ſame by the vſing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.<note n="b." place="margin">Matth. 28. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20. 1 Pet. 1.22.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are the Sacramentes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are holy ſignes and ſeales ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, ordeyned of God for that cauſe, that by them he might open vnto vs, and ſettle or confirme more largely the promiſe of the Goſpell: that is to witte, he giueth fréely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and life euerlaſting, not onely to the number of beléeuers, but to euery one that beléeueth, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely ſacrifice of Chriſt, which he made perfect vppon the croſſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 17.11 Rom. 4.11. Deut. 30.6. Leui. 6.25. Heb 9.8.9.24. Ezech. 20.12. 1. Sam. 17 36. Ieſ 6.6.7. &amp; 54.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then whether do both the worde and Sacraments tend to that end, that they may leade our faith vnto the ſacrifice of Chriſt fully ended on the croſſe, as vnto
<pb facs="tcp:28823:17"/>the ground of ſaluation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſo in déede, for the holy Ghoſte teacheth by the Goſpell, and aſſureth vs by the Sacramentes, that all our ſaluation ſtandeth in the onelye ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſte, offered for vs vppon the croſſe.<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 6.3. Gal. 3.27.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How many Sacraments hath Chriſt ordeined in the newe teſtament?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two, Baptiſme, and the holy ſupper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HOwe art thou warned and aſſured in Baptiſme that thou art partaker of that onely ſacrifice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe Chriſte commaunded the outwarde waſhing,<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 28.19 Act. 2.38.</note> putting to this promiſe:<note n="b." place="margin">Marc. 16.16 Matth. 3.11. Rom. 6.3.</note> that I am aſſuredly waſhed (by his bloud &amp; the holy Ghoſt) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the vncleannes of my ſoule, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, from all my ſinnes, as I am outwardly waſhed with water,<note n="c." place="margin">Mark. 1.4 Luk.3 3.</note> wherby all the filthines of the
<pb facs="tcp:28823:18"/>body is ſcowred away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is it to be waſhed with the bloude and ſpirite of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to receiue of God forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes freely for Chriſtes bloude ſake, which he ſhed for vs in his ſacrifice vpon the croſſe,<note n="d." place="margin">Heb. 12 24 1. Pe. 1.2. Apo 1.5. &amp; 22.14 zach. 13.1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech. 36.25.</note> and alſo to be made newe men by the holy Ghoſt, and by his making of vs holy to be made members of Chriſt, that thereby we may die from ſinne more and more, and may liue holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnblamedly.<note n="e." place="margin">Iob. 8.33. &amp; 3.5. 1. Cor. 6.11.12.13. Ro 6.4. Col. 2.12</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where promiſed Chriſte that hee would ſo ſurely waſh vs with his bloud and ſpirite, as we are waſhed outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye with the outwarde water of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the xvi. of ſaint Marke, where as he firſt ordeined Baptiſme, whoſe wordes are theſe. Goe and teach all nations, and Baptiſe them in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, and of the holy Ghoſt.<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 28.19</note> And he that will beléeue
<pb facs="tcp:28823:18"/>and be baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued, but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will not beléeue ſhalbe dampned.<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 16.16</note> and this promiſe is rehearſed again wheras the ſcripture nameth Baptiſme the bath of the newe birth,<note n="c." place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> and waſhing away of ſinnes.<note n="d." place="margin">Act. 21.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not the outwarde baptiſing with water, the waſhing away of our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not:<note n="e." place="margin">Matth. 3.12 1. Pet. 3.21. Ephe. 5.26.</note> for onely the bloude of Chriſt maketh vs cleane from all ſin.<note n="f" place="margin">Iob. 17. 1. Cor. 9.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then why doth the holy Ghoſt call baptiſme the bath of the newe birth, and waſhing away of ſinne?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God not without a great cauſe ſpeaketh ſo: to wit, not onely to teach vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as the filthines of our bodies is ſcoured away with water, ſo likewiſe are our ſins wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; ſcowred away with the bloud and ſpirite of Chriſt:<note n="g." place="margin">Apoc. 1.5. &amp; 7.8. 1. Cor. 6.11.</note> but alſo much more, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might ſicker &amp; aſſure vs by his good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly token &amp; pledge, that we are as ſurely waſhed from our ſinns inwardly by the inward waſhing, as we are outwardly waſhed with the outwarde and ſeable
<pb facs="tcp:28823:19"/>water.<note n="h." place="margin">Mark. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. Gal. 3.17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ought all yong ſpeachleſſe children in be baptiſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea in any caſe, for when as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long as well vnto the couenaunt or promiſe, and to the Church of GOD, as they doe that are fully growne and are perfect men and women,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> &amp; when as forgiueneſſe of ſinnes<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 16.14</note> and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt the<note n="c." place="margin">Luk. 1.14.15. Pſal. 22.11. Eſa. 44.1.2 Act. 2 36.</note> worker of faith, is as well promiſed to them through the bloude of Chriſt, as to them that are full growen men and women: they are to be grafted into the Church by baptiſme, and are to be knowen from the children of vnbeléeuers or infidels,<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 10.47.</note> as in the owe Teſtament, the children of them, that beléeued were knowen from them that beléeued not, by circumciſion.<note n="e." place="margin">Gen. 17.14</note> In whoſe place and ſtéede (it now being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away) Baptiſme was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note n="f." place="margin">Col. 2.12.13</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Supper of the Lord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:19"/>
               <p> HOwe art thou in the Supper of the Lorde warned, aſſured, and ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that thou art partaker of that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye one ſacrifice of Chriſt offered vppon the croſſe, and of all his good déedes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe Chriſte hath commaunded me and all faithfull men, to eate of this breade that is broken, and to drinke of this cup that is reached vnto me in the remembrance of him, with promiſe put thereto,<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 26.27.28. Mark. 14 22.23.24 Luk. 22.19.20 1 Cor. 1.16 17. &amp; 11.23.24 25. &amp; 12.13.</note> that firſt his body was aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly broken on the Croſſe and offered for me, and his bloud as ſurely ſhed for me, as I ſée the breade of the Lord bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto me, and the cuppe of the Lorde reached vnto me.</p>
               <p>More ouer that my ſoule is as wel fed vnto euerlaſting life with his body which was crucified for vs, and with his bloud whiche was ſhed for vs, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue with the mouth of my bodye the bread &amp; the wine (which are toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the body &amp; bloud of our Lord) at the handes of my ſhéepherd or elder of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is it to eate the body that was
<pb facs="tcp:28823:20"/>crucified, and to drinke the bloude that was ſhed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not onely to imbrace and receiue the whole Paſſion and death of Chriſte with a ſure truſt of minde, and to get by it forgiueneſſe of ſinnes and life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting:<note n="b." place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.40.47.48.50 51.53.54.</note> but alſo to be ſo ioyned vnto his holy body more and more through the holy ghoſt which dwelleth in Chriſte and in vs,<note n="c." place="margin">Ioh. 6.55.56</note> that although he be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen<note n="d." place="margin">Act. 3.21 Act. 1.9.1. Cor 11.26.</note> and we in earth, yet for all that we are fleſhe of his fleſhe, and bones of his bones,<note n="e." place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cor. 6.15 17.19.1. Ioh. 3.24. &amp; 4.13. Eph. 3.17.</note> and as all the members or limmes of a mans body are quickned or haue life of one ſoule, ſo are we quickned &amp; gouerned and haue life with one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.<note n="f." place="margin">Ioh. 14.23. Ioh. 6.56.57 58. Ioh. 15.1.2.3.4.5.6. Eph. 4 15.16</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In what place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>promiſed Chriſt that he woulde as ſurely giue his body and bloude to be eaten and dronken to them that beléeue, as they doe eate the breade that is broken and drinke the wine out of the cup?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the place where he did firſt ordaine
<pb facs="tcp:28823:20"/>his ſupper in theſe words.<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23. &amp;c. Marh 26.26. &amp;c. Mark. 14.22. &amp;c. Luk. 21 19. &amp;c.</note> Our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte in that night he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed tooke the breade, and after he had giuen thankes he brake it and ſaid: take eate, this is my bodie which is broken for you, doe this in the remembrance of me. And ſo likewiſe after ſupper hee tooke the cup, ſaying: this cup is the new teſtament in my bloude,<note n="b." place="margin">Exod. 24.8 Heb. 9.20.</note> doe this as oft as yée ſhal drink, in my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance,<note n="c." place="margin">Ex. 13.9.</note> For as oft as ye ſhall eate this bread and drinke of this cup, ye ſhall ſhewe the death of the Lorde till be come. i. Cor. xi. This promiſe is rehearſed againe by S. Paule. i. Cor. x. where. he ſaith: The cup of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgiuing wherw<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we giue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks is it not the pertaking of Chriſts bloud? is not the bread that we breake, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the body of Chriſt? Becauſe we being many are one breade &amp; one body,<note n="d." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16.17.</note> for we are al partakers of one bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are then bread and wine made the very body and bloud of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No but as the water of baptiſme is turned into the bloude of Chriſte, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:28823:21"/>is the waſhing away of ſinne, but onely a token and pledge of thoſe things that are ſealed vnto vs in baptiſme, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo is not the breade of the Lordes ſupper the very body of Chriſt.<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 16.29. Mark. 14.24.1. Cor. 11 26.27. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 10.16 17.</note> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, after the manner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Sacramentes, and the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med faſhion of ſpeaking of the holy ghoſt of theſe things:<note n="b." place="margin">Gen. 17.10 14.19. Exod. 12.27.43 48 &amp; 13.9. Act. 7.8. Ex. 24.8. &amp; 29.36. Leuit. 16 10. &amp;. 7.11 11 Eſ. 6.6.7. Titus. 3.5. Act. 22.6. 1. Pet. 3 2. 1. Cor. 10.1.2 3.4.</note> bread is called the body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why then doth Chriſt call bread his body, and the cup his bloude, or the new Teſtament through his bloude. And Paul calleth the breade and wine, the communion or partaking of his body &amp; bloud?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt ſpeaketh ſo, not without great conſideration: to wit, that he may not only teach vs, that euen as bread &amp; wine hold vp and kéepe in the life of the body, ſo his crucified body and his bloude that were ſhedde, are the very true meate and drinke of our ſoule, whereby it is nouriſhed into euerlaſting life:<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.51.55</note> but al ſo much more he ſpeaketh ſo, to aſſure &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:28823:21"/>ſicker vs with this viſible token and pledge, that we are as truely partakers of his body and bloude by the working of the holy Ghoſt, as wee haue receiued theſe holy tokens in the remembrance of him, with the mouth of our body:<note n="d." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16.17.</note> and alſo that his paſſion or ſuffering, and his obedience or keeping of the whole lawe, are as ſurely ours, as though wee had ſuffered our owne ſelfes for our ſinnes, and had made amendes to GOD for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What difference is there betwéene the ſupper of the Lorde, and the popiſhe Maſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſupper of the Lorde witneſſeth, that all our ſinnes are forgiuen vs through that onely one ſacrifice that he once made on the croſſe,<note n="a." place="margin">Heb. 7.27. &amp; 9.12.26.28 &amp; 10.10 12.14. Ioh. 19. Mat. 26.28.19.20</note> and that we are all through the holy ghoſt graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſt<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.17 &amp; 10.16. &amp; 12.13.</note> who after his mans nature is only in heauen at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right hand of the father,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 1.3. &amp; 8.1.</note> and will be worſhipped there of vs.<note n="d." place="margin">Ioh. 4.21 22. &amp;c. &amp; 20.17. Luk. 24.52. Act. 7.55, 56. Col. 3.1. Phi. 3.20. 1. The. 1.10.</note> But in the Maſſe it is denied that the quicke and the dead haue
<pb facs="tcp:28823:22"/>forgiueneſſe of ſinnes through the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt alone, excepte Chriſt bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered euerie day for them, by the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Maſſe prieſtes. Moreouer it is taught in the Maſſe, that Chriſt is bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie preſent vnder the likeneſſe of bread &amp; wine, and is therefore to bee worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in them.<note n="e." place="margin">In Can. Miſſae, item de conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one diſtinct. 2</note> And ſo the foundation of the Maſſe, is nothing elſe but a deniall of that onely ſacrifice and paſſion of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte and curſed Idolatrie, mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie, and worſhipping of by gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the liuing God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who ought to come to the ſupper of the Lorde?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely they that repent, and are verie ſorie that they haue angried God with their ſinnes, and yet truſt that they are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them for Chriſtes ſake, and that the reſt of their weakeneſſe and vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectnes is couered with his deth &amp; paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who alſo deſire to goe forwarde and growe more and more in holy life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. But hypocrites falſe feigners of holineſſe, and they that repente
<pb facs="tcp:28823:22"/>not and will not amende their liues, eate and drinke their owne damnation.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.21 &amp; 11.28. &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ought we alſo to allow them to this ſupper which ſhewe themſelues to bee faithles and vngodly, both in their own confeſſion and naughtie life?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No, for ſo is the couenaunt of God vnhallowed, and the wrathe of God is ſtirred againſt the whole Churche.<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 11.20.34. Eſa. 1.11. &amp;. 66.3. Iere. 7.21. &amp;c. Pſal. 50.16.</note> Wherefore the Church of God (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the appointment of Chriſte and his Apoſtles) vſing the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, ought to hold back ſuch from the Lords ſupper, vntill they repent and amend their manners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are the keyes of the kingdome of heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The preaching of the Goſpell, and correction or diſcipline of the Churche, whereby the kingdome of heauen is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them that beléeue, and is ſhut vp
<pb facs="tcp:28823:23"/>againſt them that beléeue not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe is the kingdome of heauen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and ſhut by the preaching of the Goſpell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where at the commaundemente of Chriſt we openly declare and ſhew, that all and euerie mans ſinnes are forgiuen them by God, for the onely deſeruing of Chriſte, as often as they receyue with a true faith and beléeue the promiſe of the Goſpell. Of the contrarie parte, it ſheweth vnto all them that beléeue not, and to all hipocrites, feigners of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that are wicked within, that the wrath<note n="a." place="margin">Ioh. 20.21.22.13. Math. 16.19.</note> of God, and euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation hangeth ouer their heads, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which witneſſe of the Goſpell, God will iudge as well in this life as in the life to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe is the kingdome of heauen ſhut to, or opened by the correction or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When as according vnto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:28823:23"/>of Chriſt, they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are Chriſten men in name, but ſhewe themſelues both in learninge and life farre from Chriſte,<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 12.8 1. Cor 12.21. 1. Tim. 5.17. 1. Cor. 5.4. 2 Cor. 2.6.</note> after that they haue beene certaine times brotherly warned to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their errours, and leaue their euill déeds, and are preſented or ſhewed to the Church, or to them that are appointed of the Churche vnto that office, and will not obey their warning: they are ſhutte out by the ſame, from the vſe of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and from comming to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Chriſtes Church, from God himſelfe, and the kingdome of Chriſte. But againe, if they promiſe to amende their liues, and doe ſo indéede, they are receiued into the Church againe as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and of the Church.<note n="c." place="margin">Matth. 18.15 16.17.18. 1. Cor. 5. 2. Th. 3.14.15 2. Ioh. 10.11. 2. Cor. 2.6.7.10.11.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The thirde part is of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHen as we are deliuered from all our ſinnes and wrechednes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſeruing of vs, by the onely mercie of God for Chriſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e: why
<pb facs="tcp:28823:24"/>ſhoulde we then doe good workes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe that after Chriſt hath bought vs againe with his bloude, and maketh vs newe men by his holy ſpirit, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the image of himſelfe, that we hauing receyued ſo many good turnes, ſhoulde ſhew our ſelues all our life time thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.13. &amp;. 12.12. 1. Pet. 2.5.9 10. 1. Cor. 6.10.</note> and that hee may bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.<note n="b." place="margin">Math. 5.19 1. Pet. 2.12.</note> After that we euerie man, may be aſſured of his faith by his fruits.<note n="c." place="margin">1 Pet. 1.10. Math. 7.17. Gal. 5.6.22.</note> Laſte of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may win other, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt by our honeſt and ſober life, or good example of liuing.<note n="d." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.2 Rom. 14.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can they then not be ſaued which dee vnthanksfull, and abide ſtill careleſſe in ſinne, and are not turned to God from their wickedneſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In no caſe, for the ſcripture beareth witnes that no vnchaſt perſons, neither worſhipper of ſtraunge Gods, neither horemaiſter or aduoulterers, neither co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous men, neither Théeues, nor drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes, neither ſcolding raylers, neither robbers, ſhal enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god.<note place="margin">e. Cor. 6.9 10 Eph. 5.5.6 1. Ioh. 3.14.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:24"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In what part ſtandeth the turninge of a man to God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the killing or putting downe of the olde man<note n="a." place="margin">Ro. 6.4.5.6. Ephe. 4.22.23.24. Col. 35.6.8.9.10. 1. Cor. 5.7. 2. Cor. 7.11</note> and the quickening and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp of the new man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the killing of the old man?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is truely and with all thy hearte to be ſorie that thou haſt angred GOD with thy ſinnes, and euerie day more &amp; more to hate them &amp; to flye from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 8.13. Ioel. 2.13. Oſe. 6.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the quickening or rayſing vp of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewe man?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True gladnes or God through Chriſt,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 5.1 &amp; 14.17. Ieſ. 57.15</note> and an earneſt and readie deſire of a man to order his life according to the will of God, in doing of all manner of Good workes.<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 10.11 Gal. 2.20</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are good workes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are done in faith,<note n="e." place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:28823:25"/>to the lawe of GOD<note n="f." place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22. Ephe. 2.10. &amp; 6.17.</note> and are wrought for that ende that God may be honoured therby,<note n="g" place="margin">1. Co. 10.13</note> and not they that are deuiſed by vs, and in our opinion (without the worde of God) ſéene to be good.<note n="h." place="margin">Deut. 12.32 Ez. 20.18 19 Ieſ. 29.13. Math. 15.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the lawe of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath ſpoken all theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Exod. 20. Deut. 5.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The tenne Commandementes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I.</hi> I am the Lorde thy God whiche hath brought thée out of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage. Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods in my ſight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Thou ſhalt make to thée no grauen image, nor the likenes of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, nor in the water vnder the earth. Thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them nor worſhippe them: for I the Lorde thy God am a ielouſe God, and viſite the ſinnes of the fathers vppon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnto the third and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:28823:25"/>of them that hate mee, and ſhewe mercie vnto thouſandes in them that loue me and kéepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements. The <hi>III.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine, for the Lorde will not hold him giltles that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his name in vaine.</p>
               <p>The <hi>IIII.</hi> Remember thou kéepe holye the Sabboth daye. Sixe dayes ſhalte thou labour and doe all that thou haſte to do, but the ſeuenth day is the Saboth of the Lorde thy God, in it thou ſhalt do no maner of worke, thou and thy ſonne and thy daughter, thy man ſeruaunt and thy maide ſeruant, thy cattell, and the ſtraunger that is within thy gate. For in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen and earth, the ſea &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in them, and reſted the ſeuenth day: wherefore the Lorde bleſſed the ſeuenth day and hallowed it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>V.</hi> Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy dayes may be long in the lande whiche the Lorde thy God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thée.</p>
               <p>The <hi>VI.</hi> Thou ſhalte doe no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:26"/>
               <p> The <hi>VII.</hi> Thou ſhalt not do aduoutrie.</p>
               <p>The <hi>VIII.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p>The <hi>IX.</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               <p>The <hi>X.</hi> Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, nor his wife, not his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, nor his maide, nor his oxe nor his Aſſe, nor ane thing that is his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe are theſe commaundementes deuided?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into two tables;<note n="a." place="margin">Exo. 34.28. Deut 4.13. &amp; 10.3.4.</note> of the which the former teacheth in it, foure commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, how that we ſhall behaue our ſelues towarde God. The ſeconde table teacheth in it ſixe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, what duetie, good deedes, and gentleneſſe, we owe vnto our neighbour.<note n="b." place="margin">Math. 22.38</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What requireth God of vs, in the firſt table?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That euen ſo dearely as I loue the ſaluation of my ſoule, ſo earneſtly ſhould I ſhunne and flye Idolatrie,<note n="c." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9.10. &amp; 10.7.14</note> Maume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie or worſhipping of falſe gods, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chraft,<note n="d." place="margin">Leuit. 18.13 Deut. 18.11.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28823:26"/>Sorcerie, Enchauntmentes, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition or worſhipping of God, by other meanes then hee hath taught in his worde, calling for helpe of Saintes or any other creatures<note n="e." place="margin">Mat. 4.10. Apo. 19.10. &amp; 22.8.9.</note> But that I ſhould rightly confeſſe and acknowledge the only and true God,<note n="a." place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> and only truſt in him,<note n="b." place="margin">Ier. 17.5.</note> and ſhould with great lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note n="c." place="margin">1. Pet. 5.5.6</note> ſubmitte my ſelfe vnto him,<note n="d." place="margin">Heb. 10.36. Col. 1.11. Rom. 5.3.4. 1. Cor. 10.10. Phi. 2.14.</note> and looke for all good thinges of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,<note n="e." place="margin">Pſa. 104.27.28.29.30. Eſa. 45.7.</note> and that with all my heart and withal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſires of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame I ſhould loue him<note n="f." place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Math. 22.37.</note> and with reuerence worſhip &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him ſo much,<note n="g." place="margin">Deut. 6.2. Pſal. 111.10. Pro. 1.7. Math. 10.18. Math. 4.10. Deut. 10.20.</note> that I had leauer forſake all creatures, then to doe anye thing contrarie to his will.<note n="h." place="margin">Math. 5.29 30. &amp; 10.37. Act. 5.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is idolatrie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in the ſtede of one God, or beſide him that is the true God, who hath ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſhewed himſelfe plainely and clearely in his worde, to feigne, make or haue any thing, wherein thou beléeueſt or putteſt thy hope in.<note n="i." place="margin">Eph. 5.5 1. Par. 16.26. Phil. 3.19. Gal. 4.8 Ephe. 2.12. 1. Ioh. 2.23. 2. Ioh. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What requireth the ſecond commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:27"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we ſhoulde not ſhewe, ſet out, or expreſſe god, by any Image or figure,<note n="k." place="margin">Deut. 4.15. &amp;c. Ieſ. 40.18 Rom. 1.23. Act. 17.29</note> neither ſhoulde we worſhippe him any other wiſe then he hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his word himſelfe to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.<note n="l" place="margin">Sam. 15 23 Deut. 12.30 Math. 15.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether then ought any images or, likeneſſe of thinges to be made?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God neither ought, neither can by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes bee counterfetted, ſhewed, or declared, by any caſter, Founder, Kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or Painter. And although they bee ſuffred to expreſſe creatures, as herbes, trées, fiſhes, and birdes, and ſuch like: yet GOD forbiddeth their images to be made or had, that through them wee ſhould worſhippe or honour God, or giue to them any worſhip, or outwarde reuerence.<note n="a." place="margin">Exo. 33.24. &amp; 34.13. Num. 33.52. Deut. 2.5. &amp; 12.3. &amp; 16.22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. reg. 18.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether ought images to be ſuffered to ſtand in Churches to bee lay mens bookes or nor?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:27"/>
               <p> No no. For it is not ſéemely that we ſhould be wiſer then God, who willeth that his Church ſhould bee taught with the liuely preaching of his word,<note n="b." place="margin">2. Timo. 3.16.17. 2. Pet. 1.19.</note> and not with dumme images.<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 10.8 Hab. 2.18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What doth God ordayne in the third commandemente</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we ſhould not onely, not vſe his name ſpitfully &amp; vnreuerently in ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, curſing, forſwearing,<note n="d." place="margin">Leui. 24.11 &amp;c. Le 19.12</note> and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without a iuſt cauſe in any manner of ſwearing at all,<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 5.37 Iac. 5.12.</note> neither ſhould we he partakers of thoſe horrible and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſins, either by holding of our peace, or in wincking at them, but that wee ſhould vſe that holy name of God no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but with deuotion, reuerence, and worſhip<note n="f." place="margin">Eſay. 45.23</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may be worſhipped &amp; honoured in all our wordes and deeds<note n="g." place="margin">Rom. 2.24 1. Tim. 6.1 Col. 5.16.</note> with a true &amp; ſtedfaſt comeſſione<note n="h." place="margin">Mat. 10.32</note> &amp; inuocation or<note n="i." place="margin">1. Tim. 2 8.</note> calling vpon his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it then ſo gréeuous a ſin, to diſhonor the name of God in ſwearing &amp; in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that God is alſo angrie with them
<pb facs="tcp:28823:28"/>that will not aſmuch as lyeth in them) hinder, forbid, and let it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely it is the moſt gréeuous ſinne,<note n="a." place="margin">Leu. 5.1.</note> neither is there any that angreth and diſpleaſeth him more, then the ſpightfull miſuſing of his name. Wherfore it was his wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it ſhold be puniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deth.<note n="b." place="margin">Leu. 24.15.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May not a man ſometime godly and lawfully, ſweare by the name of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He may. Either when the Magiſtrate Gods officer requireth or commandeth a man to ſwear, or otherwiſe when néed requireth, that by this meane a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may get credit, and the trueth may be proued and ſtabliſhed therewith, that thereby God may be glorified and praiſed, &amp; men may be holpen thereby. For ſuch a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful othe is approued as holy by the word of God,<note n="c." place="margin">Deu. 6.13. &amp; 10.20. Eſay, 48.1. Heb. 6.16.</note> and therfore it was wel vſed of the fathers both in the olde and newt Teſtament.<note n="d." place="margin">Gen. 21.24. &amp;. 31.53. Ieſ. 9.15.19. 1. Sam. 24.23 2. Sam. 3.25. 1. Reg. 1.29. Rom. 1.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it lawfull for a man to ſweare by ſaintes or other creatures?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:28"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Noe, for a lawfull othe is the calling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, or inuocation of God, that he (as onely the knower of the ſecretes of the heart) may giue witneſſe vnto the truth and puniſh the ſwearer (if wittingly he ſweare falſely)<note n="e." place="margin">2. Cor. 1.13.</note> but this honour is to be giuen vnto no creature.<note n="f." place="margin">Math. 5.34.35.36. Iac. 5.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What hath God commaunded in the fourth commaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt that the ſeruing in the office of preaching and miniſtring of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and that the ſcholes ſhould bee kept, mainteined and prouided for,<note n="a." place="margin">Titus. 1.5. 1. Ti. 3.1. Cor 9.11.13.14. 2. Tim. 2.2. &amp; 3.15. 1. Tim. 4.13. &amp; 5.17.</note> that I on the hollyday and at other times when the Church is (for ſome neceſſarie cauſe gathered together.) ſhoulde ioyne my ſelfe vnto that holy fellowſhippe, to heare the word of God diligently &amp; héed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.19 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.31.</note> and to vſe the ſacraments,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Co. 11.31</note> 
                  <note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 68.27 &amp; 40.10.11. Act. 2.42.46.</note> &amp; wyne my praiers with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon praiers,<note n="e." place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.2 3.8.9. 1 Cor. 14.15.</note> &amp; giue ſomthing according to my rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore<note n="f." place="margin">1. Cor. 16.2</note> &amp; afterward for all my life time, kéepe holliday and forbeare from all ill déedes, giuing place, and
<pb facs="tcp:28823:29"/>graunting vnto God that throughe his holy ſpirite, he may work his workes in me: and ſo may beginne the euerlaſting Sabboth or holy day in this life.<note n="g." place="margin">Ieſ. 66.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What inioyneth God vs to do in the fift commaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we ſhould giue due honour, and ſhewe faithfulneſſe to our fathers and mothers, and to all that are gouernours ouer vs, and ſhould ſubmitte our ſelues with all conuenient obedience, vnto their faithfull commaundementes and chaſtening<note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 6.2.5 &amp;c. Col. 3.18.20.22.23.24 Ephe. 5.22. Pro. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 4.1. &amp; 15.20 &amp; 20.20. Exo. 21.17 Rom. 13</note> and that we ſhould ſuffer &amp; be are with their vices and maners<note n="i." place="margin">Prou 23.22 Gen. 9.25. 1. Pet. 2.18</note> euer thinking this in our minde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God wil gouern &amp; guide vs by their hand<note n="k." place="margin">Ephe. 6.4.9 Col. 3.19 Rom. 13.21. Math. 22.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What doeth God require in the ſixte commaundemente</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I ſhoulde do no iniurie wrong or reproch to my neighbour neither with my wordes, geſture or outwarde beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, either by my ſelfe, or by anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, hate him, hurte him, or kill
<pb facs="tcp:28823:29"/>him,<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 5.21 22 Gen. 9.6. Matth. 26.52.</note> but to leaue and giue ouer al the deſire of reuenging<note n="b." place="margin">Eph 4.26. Rom. 12.19. Matth. 5.25 &amp; 18.35.</note> vnto god: neither that I ſhoulde hurt my ſelfe, nor caſt my ſelfe wittingly into any ieoperdie.<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 13.14 Co. 2.23. Syr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 27. Mat. 4.7.</note> Wherefore God hath armed the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his officer with the ſworde, that there ſhould no murder be done.<note n="d." place="margin">Gen. 9.6. Exod. 21.14. Matth. 26.52 Rom. 13.4</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth this commaundement onely forbid manſlaughter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Almightie God by forbidding of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, teacheth that he hateth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> roote and beginning of murder: anger,<note n="e." place="margin">Iac. 1.20. Gal. 5.20.</note> enuy,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 1.29.</note> hatred,<note n="g." place="margin">1. Io 2.9.11.</note> and deſire of wreaking or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging, and that hee taketh all theſe thinges for murder.<note n="h." place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it ynough for vs to kill no man, by thoſe meanes that are before rehear, ſede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it not ynough? For when as God forbiddeth anger, enuie, and hatred: hee requireth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ſhoulde loue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelues,<note n="i." place="margin">Matth. 22 39 &amp;. 7 12.</note> ſhoulde vſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde them gentleneſſe,<note n="k." place="margin">Rom. 12.10</note> mildnes,<note n="l." place="margin">Eph. 4.2. Gal. 6.1.2. Matth. 5.5. Rom. 12.18.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28823:30"/>méekeneſſe, patience and mercy,<note n="m." place="margin">Math. 5.7. Luk. 6.36.</note> and to turne away or ſtop (aſmuch as lyeth in vs) ſuch thinges as may be hurtefull vnto them.<note n="n." place="margin">Exo. 23.5.</note> And finally that wes ſhoulde be ſo minded toward them, that we ſhould bee good euen vnto our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.<note n="a." place="margin">Matth. 1.44 45. Rom. 12.20.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the meaning of the ſeuenth commaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That God defieth all filthineſſe,<note n="b." place="margin">Leuit. 18.27.28.</note> and therefore we ought alſo to hate it, &amp; vtterly to defie it,<note n="c." place="margin">Iuda. 23.</note> and that we ſhould liue contrarie vnto all vncleaneſſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly, ſoberly and chaſtly<note n="d." place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.34.5.</note> both in holy wedlocke and alſo in ſingle lyfe.<note n="e." place="margin">Heb. 13.7. 1. Cor. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth God forbide no more in this commaundement, but aduoultrie, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſuch kindes of filthineſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When as our bodyes and ſoules are the Churches or Temples of the Holye Ghoſt, the will of GOD is, that wée ſhoulde kéepe them both cleane, and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb facs="tcp:28823:30"/>vnto him, and therefore vtterly forbiddeth all déedes, ſignes, tokens, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and words, or<note n="f." place="margin">Eph. 5.3.4. 1. Cor. 6.18.19.20.</note> filthy deſires<note n="g." place="margin">Math. 5.28</note> and what ſoeuer intiſeth a man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.<note n="h." place="margin">Eph. 5 18. 1. Cor. 15.33.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What doth God forbid in the eighte commaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not onely ſuch theftes<note n="i." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.10.</note> and robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries<note n="k." place="margin">1. Cor. 5.10</note> as the common officers doe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe:<note n="l." place="margin">Luk. 3 14 1. Theſſ. 4.6.</note> but he vnderſtandeth vnder the name of theft, all craftie fetches, driftes, ſubtile meanes and wayes, whereby we hawke &amp; ly in wait, to take other mens goods from them, or laboure to conuaye them vnto vs, either by might or viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or by any falſe pretence of righte, as though we had a iuſt title to them, &amp; yet haue none at al. Such meanes are falſe weights,<note n="a." place="margin">Prou. 11.1. &amp; 16.11.</note> falſe yeardes, elles, and falſe meaſures,<note n="b." place="margin">Exech. 45.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</note> counterfeite and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ware, counterfeite and vnlawefull money, vſurie,<note n="c." place="margin">Deut. 25.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c. Pſal. 15.5 Luk. 6.35.</note> and all vnlawefull meanes and wayes that God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to get mans liuing withal. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto may be put &amp; ioyned al couetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:28823:31"/>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.10</note> and vnthriftie and prodigall powring out, and ſpending and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Gods gifts, and euil vſing of the ſame.<note n="e" place="margin">Prou. 5.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are thoſe thinges which God commaundeth here?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That as much as is poſſible, I ſhould helpe and increaſe the goods and profite of my neighbour. And that I ſhoulde do ſo vnto him, as I woulde he ſhoulde doe vnto me,<note n="f" place="margin">Matt. 7.7.12</note> and that I ſhoulde doe my worke earneſtly, truely and faithfully, that I may thereby he able to reléeue &amp; helpe them that haue néede.<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 4.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What requireth the ninth comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I ſhall not beare falſe witneſſe againſt any man,<note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 19.5.9. &amp; 21.28.</note> neither falſly turne the meaning of any mans wordes,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.3.</note> neither ſhall backebite any man, or ſpitefully raile againſte any man,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.18.30.</note> neither ſhall raſhly without the ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a lawefull cauſe, condempne any
<pb facs="tcp:28823:31"/>man.<note n="l" place="margin">Matth. 7.1. &amp;c. Luk. 6.37</note> But with all the meanes that I can, I ſhall flye and eſchewe all kinde of lyes and deceiptes,<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 12.22 &amp; 13.5.1. Cor 13.6.</note> as the proper workes of the diuell,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> except I be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſtirre vp againſt mee, the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous wrath of God. In iudgements and other matters I ſhall followe it that is true, and ſtedfaſtly and fréely tell and confeſſe the matter as it is in déede,<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 4.25.</note> and moreouer I ſhal (as much as I can) defend and increaſe the good name, fame, and credite of my neighbours.<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What forbiddeth the tenth comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That our heartes ſhould not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or ſtirred vp, with ſo much as with the leaſt thought or deſire, againſt anye of Gods commandements, but that we ſhal hate and defie at al times al kind of ſinne, &amp; ſhal delite our ſelues in all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 7.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can they that are turned to GOD kéepe perfectly, and fully, theſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:32"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No, for euen the holyeſt amongeſt all men (as longe as they liue here) haue but ſmall beginnings of this obedience,<note n="f" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.8. Rom. 7.14.15 &amp;c. Eccl. 7.21</note> But yet go ſo farre, that they earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (with no feigned deſire) begin to liue not onely according vnto ſome of theſe commaundementes, but accordinge to all the commaundementes of God.<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 7.22. Iac. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why will God then that his lawe ſhoulde be ſo earneſtly and ſharply prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched when there is no man in this lyfe, that is able to keepe it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that all the time of our life we ſhall confeſſe and acknowledge<note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.9 Pſal. 32.5.</note> howe greately we are diſpoſed of nature to ſin, and ſo thereby that we more gréedelye, and with agreater deſire, call for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 7.24 25.</note> and that we ſhoulde alwayes be occupied in this, that we alwayes bee hinking and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording with our ſelues of Godlineſſe, and call vppon the Father for the grace of the holy Ghoſte, that we may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
<pb facs="tcp:28823:32"/>and faſhioned to the likeneſſe of God euerie day more and more, vntill at the length, after that we bee departed out of this life: we may with ioye and gladneſſe get the full perfectneſſe, that is propoſed, ſet foorth, and required of vs.<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 9 2.4 Phil. 3.11.12.13.14.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVHy is prayer neceſſarie for a Chriſtian man?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe it is the chiefe part of that thankefulneſſe that God requireth of vs.<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 50.14 15.</note> And alſo becauſe God onely giueth them his grace and holy ſpirite, who with true vnfeigned growninges are of him things neceſſarie, &amp; giue him thanks for ſuch benefites as they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.<note n="e" place="margin">Matth. 7 Luk. 11.13 Math. 13.12. Pſal. 50.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What thinges are required in that prayer which ſhall pleaſe God, and bee heard of him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:33"/>
               <p> That wee ſhoulde aſke of the onely true God which hath opened himſefe in his worde<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 4.22</note> all thoſe thinges which he hath commaunded to bee axed, with a true deſire of the hearte,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.26. 1. Ioh. 5.14 Ioh. 4.23.24. Pſal. 145.18 1.2. Par. 20.12</note> and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde féeling of our geggerly néede and wretchedneſſe, <hi>(c)</hi> and caſt our ſelues downe humbly and lowly in the ſight of Gods maieſtie,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 2.11. &amp; 34.19. Ieſ. 66.2.</note> &amp; leane to this ſure foundation,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.14 &amp; 8.15. Iac. 1.6</note> that although we be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie, yet we ſhall ſurely be heard for Chriſtes ſake<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 14.13.14.15. &amp;. 15.16 &amp; 16.23. Dan. 9.17.18</note> as he hath promiſed vs in his worde.<note n="g" place="margin">Matth. 7.8. Pſal. 143.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are thoſe thinges that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to be axed of him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All thinges that are neceſſarie both for bodie and ſoule,<note n="h" place="margin">Iac. 1.17. Matth. 6.33.</note> which our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte conteineth in his prayer that he hath taught vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is that prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>OVr Father<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 6.9. &amp;c. Luk. 11.2. &amp;c.</note> which arte in heauen, halowed be thy name. Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come. Thy will be done in earth
<pb facs="tcp:28823:33"/>as it is in heauen. Giue vs this day our dayly bread. And forgiue vs our dettes, as we forgiue our debters. And leade vs not into temptation. But deliuer vs from euill. For thine is the kingdome, the power and the glorie, for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why doth Chriſt commaund that we ſhould call God our father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he might ſtirre vp in vs euen in the verie beginning of our prayer, ſuch reuerence as is méet for the ſonnes of God, and a bolde truſt toward GOD, which is, to be the ground of our prayer, to wit, that God through Chriſt is made our father, and will much leſſe deny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs thoſe thinges that we aſke of him with a true faith: then our earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will deny vnto vs earthly thinges<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 7.9.10.11. Kuk. 11.11.12.13</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is it ſayd further, which art in heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we ſhoulde not thinke to vylely,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:34"/>baſely, or earthly, of his heauenly maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,<note n="b." place="margin">Ier. 22.23.24. Act. 17.24.25.27</note> and that we ſhould looke for, and waite of his almightines, for all things whatſoeuer are neceſſary for our ſoules and bodyes.<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 10.12</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the firſt petition or aſking?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Halowed be thy name, that is to ſay: at the beginning grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs that we may rightly knowe thée,<note n="d." place="margin">Ioh. 17.3 Ier. 9 23.24 &amp; 31.33.34. Math. 16.17. Iac. 1.5. Pſal. 105.119.</note> &amp; worſhip, praiſe, and honour thy almightineſſe, thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe and gentleneſſe, thy mercie and thy trueth<note n="e." place="margin">Pſa. 119.137 Luk. 1.49. &amp;c 68. &amp;c. Pſal. 145.8.9.17. Exod. 34.67. Pſal. 143.1 2 10.11.12. Ier 31.3. &amp;. 32.1. 19.40.41. &amp; 33.11.20. Mat. 19.17. Rom. 3.3.4. &amp;. 11.22.33.1. Tim 2 19.</note> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde purpoſe and driue all our life, our thoughtes wordes and déedes vnto this end, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy moſt holy name be not blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med or euill ſpoken of for vs, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be highly honoured and prayſed.<note n="a." place="margin">Pſal. 115.1. &amp; 71.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the ſeconde peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy kingdome come. That is, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne vs ſo with thy worde and ſpirite that we may humble and ſubmitte our ſelues more and more vnto thée,<note n="b." place="margin">Math. 6.33 Pſal. 119.5.142.10.</note> kéepe &amp; increaſe thy church,<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 51.20. &amp; 122.6.</note> deſtroye
<pb facs="tcp:28823:34"/>ſhe workes of the diuell, and all power that litteth it ſelfe againſt thy maieſtie: diſapoint and make voide and of none effect, all the counſelles that are taken a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt thy worde,<note n="d." place="margin">5. Ioh. 3.8. Rom. 16.20.</note> vntill thou maiſt (at the length) reigne and rule full and perfectly<note n="e." place="margin">Apo. 22.17 20. Rom. 8.22 23.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt be al in al.<note n="f." place="margin">2. Cor. 15.28</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the thiroe petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen. That is, graunt that we and all men renouncing and forſaking our owne willes<note n="g." place="margin">Mat. 26.24. Tit. 2.12.</note> may be obedient, redily bent, and without any grudge vnto the kéeping of thy will which is onely holy,<note n="h." place="margin">Luk. 22.42.</note> and that ſo euerie one of vs, may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill and doe the office that is appointed vnto vs, faithfully and cherefully,<note n="i." place="margin">1. Cor. 7.2</note> as the Angels do in Heauen.<note n="k." place="margin">Pſal. 103.20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the fourth peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Giue vs this day our daily breade. That is, giue vnto vs all thinges which are néedful and neceſſarie for this life,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 145.25. &amp; 140.2. &amp;c. Mat. 6.25. &amp;c.</note> that through the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:28823:35"/>and confeſſe that thou art onely the well out of the which all goodnes doth ſpring,<note n="a." place="margin">Act 17.27. Deut. 8.3. &amp;. 14.17.</note> and that all our care &amp; labour, &amp; alſo thy owne giftes are vnlucky &amp; noyſome vnto vs, except thou do bleſſe them and giue them increaſe.<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 15. Deut. 8.3. Pſal. 27.16.37.</note> Wherfore grant vs to turne away our truſt from all creatures, and to put it onelye in thée.<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 6.11. &amp;. 55.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the fift petition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Forgiue vs our debttes, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our debters. That is, for Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloude ſake, lay not to our charge that are wretched ſinners, all our ſinne, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crooked frowardneſſe which cleaueth in vs ſtil<note n="d." place="margin">Pſal. 51<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. &amp;c. 143.2. 1. Ioh. 2.1.2.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we doe féele this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy grace in our harts, that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende and purpoſe ſtedfaſtly to forgiue vnfeignedly with our minde all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue hurte or gréeued vs, or haue done vs any wrong.<note n="e." place="margin">Ma. 6.14.15</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the ſixt peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Leade vs not into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation. But deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:28823:35"/>vs from euill. That is, becauſe wee are ſo féeble and weake of nature, that we cannot, one minute of an houre with out helpe ſtand ſtedfaſtly and not bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, and our moſt gréeuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, the diuel,<note n="g." place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8. Eph. 6.12</note> the world,<note n="h." place="margin">Ioh. 15.19</note> and our owne ſleſho<note n="i." place="margin">Rom. 7.23. Gal. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> vnſeaſſably do fighte againſt vs. Thou O our almightie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold vp and ſtay vs, and ſtrengthen vs by the might of the holy Ghoſt, that we fall not down and be ouercommed in this ſpirituall fight,<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 26.41 Mark. 13.33.</note> but ſo long wee may ſtoutly withſtand them, vntill that we may get at length, the whole victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<note n="b." place="margin">1. Theſſ. 3 13. &amp; 5.23</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howe maketh hee an ende of this prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thine is the kingdom, the power and the glorie for euer. Amen. That is to ſay, we aſke all theſe thinges of thée, becauſe thou art both our king, and art almightie, and both will, and can giue al theſe thinges vnto vs,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 10.11 12.2. Pet. 2 9</note> and theſe thinges doe we therefore craue of thée, that by them, al honour, glorie, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:28823:36"/>ſhould come vnto thy holy name &amp; not to vs.<note n="d." place="margin">Ioh. 14.13 Pſal. 11.5.1. Ier. 33.8.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What meaneth this worde amen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the matter is ſure and out of al doubt, &amp; that my prayer is much more ſurely harde of God, then I doe féele in my hart, that I deſire it to be graunted.<note n="e." place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20 2. Tim. 2.13.</note>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:36"/>
            <head>¶ A Table of the contentes of this Cathechiſme.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the onely comforte, both in this life and at our departure.</item>
               <item>Of the wretchedneſſe of man.</item>
               <item>That we haue no fréewill or choyce of our ſelues.</item>
               <item>Of the wrath of God for our ſinnes.</item>
               <item>Of the mercie of God.</item>
               <item>Of the righteouſneſſe, or ſtreight puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of God.</item>
               <item>Of the deliuerance of man.</item>
               <item>Of ſatiſfaction or making amends for ſinne.</item>
               <item>Who is our meane or mediator.</item>
               <item>What faith is.</item>
               <item>What thinges are neceſſarie to beléeue.</item>
               <item>Of the créede, or articles of our faith.</item>
               <item>Of the prouidence of God.</item>
               <item>Of the going downe of Chriſt to hell.</item>
               <item>That onely faith iuſtifieth.</item>
               <item>Of the Sacraments.</item>
               <item>Of Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>The Lordes ſupper.</item>
               <item>That Chriſt is not really, bodily, or fleſhly, in the ſupper.</item>
               <item>Of the keies of the kingdome of heauen.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28823:37"/>
               <item>Wherefore we muſt do good workes.</item>
               <item>Of the mortification or killing of the old man and of our fleſhly luſtes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</item>
               <item>The x. commaundementes.</item>
               <item>What is idolatrie.</item>
               <item>Of inuocacion, or calling vppon ſaints. for helpe.</item>
               <item>Againſt the vſe of Images.</item>
               <item>That the commaundements cannot be kept fully or perfectly.</item>
               <item>Of prayer.</item>
               <item>The expoſition of the Lords prayer.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:28823:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
